Black holes are the most powerful and extreme things in the universe
ブラックホールは宇宙でもっとも極端な存在で
and they are wildly weird and complicated.
全く奇妙で複雑だ
What would happen if you fell inside one and what are they really?
もし中に落ちたら？
というか、そもそもなんなのだろうか？
First we need to talk about space and time:
まず、空間と時間について知る必要がある
Space and time are the grand stage where the play of the universe unfolds.
空間と時間は宇宙のための大舞台だが
But space isn't a fixed stage and time doesn't tick the same for everyone everywhere.
空間は舞台のように固定されておらず
時間の流れ方も場所によって異なる
In short, they are relative.
要は、これらは相関性があるのだ
Matter bends space and bent space tells matter how to move.
物質は空間を曲げ
空間は物質の動き方を決める
Put some stars and planets on the stage, and it sags underneath them.
恒星や惑星を置くと
その下の空間は歪み
That misshapen stage, with all its little warps and dips, gives us gravity.
その小さな歪みや凹みが
重力を与えてくれるのだ
Black holes do not just bend the stage, they are like trap doors.
だがブラックホールは舞台を曲げるに留まらず
落とし穴となる
Places with so much mass that the universe formed a 'no-go' zone
あまりにも大きな質量によって
世界のルールは変更され
where the rules change.
"立入禁止"が形成されるのだ
Most black holes form when very massive stars die.
多くのブラックホールは
巨大な星の死と共に生まれた
We explained this process in detail in our neutron star video
過去の中性子星の動画でも詳しく説明したが
– all you need to know now, that in the final moments of really massive stars,
巨星の本当に最後の瞬間
their insides implode, at nearly a quarter of the speed of light.
その内部は光速の1/4の速度で崩壊し
This packs so much mass, so close together that it creates something so dense
より多くの質量がまとまることで
非常に密度の高い
that it sort of breaks the stage of the universe.
宇宙のルールを破壊する
モノとなった
A black hole with ten times the mass of the sun would be barely 60 kilometers across.
フラックホールは重さが太陽の10倍でも
大きさはわずか60kmだ
If you look directly at a black hole it looks like... nothing.
もしブラックホールを直視しても
なにも見えないだろう
The space under their control is blocked by an invisible,
その支配領域は見えない一方通行の
one-way border called the event horizon.
事象の地平線という境界で遮られている
The event horizon forms a shell around a region of space that,
事象の地平線は領域を囲む境界であり
once entered, is shielded from the rest of the universe forever.
侵入する者は宇宙から永遠に隔離される
Because the black hole trap door deforms space so much, not even light can escape it.
ブラックホールは空間を曲げすぎて
光すら逃さない落とし穴と化している
And with nothing escaping to transfer information from the inside, it's impossible to tell what it really looks like.
内側の情報は全く漏れ聞こえてこないため
外観を知ることはできない
We still can observe black holes because of their effect on matter.
それでも観察できるのは
物質に影響を与えるからだ
Things can orbit black holes just as they can orbit the sun or a planet.
太陽や惑星のように
ブラックホールも物質を周回させる
Many black holes have discs of matter orbiting outside the event horizon.
多くのブラックホールの外側を
物質が円盤状に周回している
This matter can become incredibly hot
これらは信じがたいほど熱く
as close orbits can speed this matter up to half the speed of light,
軌道の近いものは光速の半分ほどまで加速し
and tiny amounts of friction and collisions between particles heat them to a billion degrees,
粒子同士の摩擦や衝突により
数十億℃まで加熱され
making the space around these black holes, ironically, incredibly bright.
周囲を、皮肉なほど明るく照らしている
What would happen if you would try to get close, or even inside a black hole?
近づいたり中に入るとどうなるだろうか？
First of all, you would see the strangest funhouse mirror in the universe.
まず、宇宙一不思議な
鏡のようなものを見るだろう
Matter isn't the only thing orbiting a black hole:
ブラックホールでは物質のみでなく
gravity is so strong near them that light can orbit too.
強力すぎる重力により光すらも周回している
If you hovered just outside the event horizon, at the photon sphere,
もし事象の地平線のすぐ外側に浮いていたとしたら
in any direction you'd just see... yourself!
たとえどの方向を向いても
自分が見えるだろう
Straight ahead would be the back of your own head, as light from your back travels around the black hole to your eyes.
自分が発した光が
ブラックホールを回り目に入るためだ
Gravity also alters the passage of time itself.
重力は時間の流れも変化させる
The stronger the gravity, the slower time passes.
重力が強いほど
時間の流れも遅くなる
While you watch the universe above you speed up, those far away will watch you in slow motion.
宇宙の加速を眺めているあなたは
観測者にはスローモーションに見える
If you chose to fly away from the black hole, you might find that eons have passed for the rest of the universe,
もしブラックホールから旅立つとしたら
外は悠久の時が経っていて
a freakish one-way time-travel trip to the future where your loved ones are long dead.
愛する者もとっくに亡くなった
一方通行の時間跳躍を体験できる
But getting close to a black hole can be incredibly dangerous.
ブラックホールに近づくのは
危険なことだ
A painful death by 'spaghettification' awaits you.
スパゲッティ化現象なる
痛ましい死が訪れる
Because your feet are closer to the black hole than your head
足は頭よりブラックホールに近いため
they feel a stronger pull of gravity, enough to pull you apart.
下半身がモゲそうなほど
重力で強く引っ張られる
As you descend it gets worse, the pulling gets stronger, your body squeezed thinner and straighter
下降するほどに重力は強くなり
体は細く長く絞られ
until you've been reduced to a thin stream of hot plasma, gobbled up in one final slurp, never to be seen again.
最終的に細いプラズマとなり
吸い込まれて二度とお目にかかれなくなる
Spaghettification is only a risk with smaller black holes, since they have much smaller radii.
スパゲッティ化現象は
小さなブラックホールにのみおきる
If you go to the center of a galaxy and find a supermassive black hole,
銀河の中心にあるような
超大質量ブラックホールなら
you might be able to experience crossing the event horizon.
事象の地平線を越えられるかもしれない
As you approach the event horizon, a distant observer would think they never saw you enter it,
あなたが中に入ろうとしても
観測者はその瞬間を見ることなく
seeing you stop and fade.
静止し消滅するのを目にする
The last light you emit trickling up and out, away from the event horizon.
あなたが発した最後の光は
事象の地平線からゆっくり洩れていく
Meanwhile, from your perspective the void of the black hole rises up to meet you,
一方、あなたの視点では
一部方向の光しか届かないため
as light from fewer directions can reach you.
虚空に包まれるように見える
The blackness envelopes you until your only view of the universe you left
暗闇に包まれ
見えるものはわずか
is a tiny spot of light.
点のような光だけになる
Here, inside the event horizon, space and time are so horribly broken
事象の地平線内は
空間も時間もしっちゃかめっちゃかで
that real time travel is possible,
時間跳躍すら現実となり
so it's probably a good thing that nothing gets out.
堅牢さに
感謝するぐらいかもしれない
If anything could escape it could create all sorts of time travel paradoxes
もし出られれば
タイムパラドックスを引き起こし
and issues that break the universe.
宇宙が破綻してしまうかも
As scary as the event horizon is, it keeps us safe from that drama.
事象の地平線はそんなドラマから
我々を守っているのだ
Whether you have survived this long doesn't really matter,
今やあなたの生死は
実はどうでも良くて
as now there is only the certainty of crushing death in your near future.
近く確実に圧死する
未来が待っている
Inside the event horizon space time itself is so bent and warped,
事象の地平線の中は時空が歪みすぎて
that whatever direction you move here, every "forward" you go,
どの方向に前進したとしても
leads only towards the center of the black hole.
ブラックホールの中心に向かってしまう
Trying to go any direction only brings you to the center faster.
どの方向に行こうとしても
より中心に進むだけだ
To survive the longest, you must do: nothing.
長生きしたいと思ったら
何もしない方がいい
In the center of the black hole, we find the singularity.
ブラックホールの中心には
特異点がある
A single point with all the matter that has ever crossed the event horizon,
事象の地平線を越えてきた全ての物質は
all crushed to a point infinitely small.
この無限小の点に集まっている
There is no memory of the things that made it as stuff disappears down the black hole trapdoor forever.
物質だったころの情報は一切が消え去り
永久に閉じ込められる
The singularity makes all things equal.
特異点は全てのもの等しくする
This actually breaks the universe in really cool ways.
このようにクールな方法で
宇宙を壊しているのだ
We made a whole video about this problem if you want to learn more.
詳しく知りたければ
過去に動画も作ったが
But in a nutshell, everything that comes too close becomes black hole matter,
要するに、近づいたものは
ブラックホール物質となり
concentrated at the singularity.
特異点に集中するのだ
This lack of a memory of its past, means that a black hole has only three properties:
過去を忘却したブラックホールは
性質がたった3つしかない
their mass, spin, and electric charge.
質量、スピン、電荷だ
Everything else is lost.
それ以外の全ては失われた
They're a lot like fundamental particles in that respect.
その点は素粒子とよく似ている
This actually means that every single black hole in the universe is the same.
つまり宇宙に数あるブラックホールは
みな同じともいえる
Sure, their mass is different and some spin faster than others.
確かに質量や回転速度は違うが
But If we were to put all the singularities into a magical physics museum,
もし特異点を展示する
博物館があれば
they would be identical, like electrons.
電子のように均一に見えるはずだ
But just like fundamental particles, the properties of singularities are the best ways we can describe them on paper,
しかしこれらの説明はあくまでも
机上で表現できる最善にすぎず
rather than an accurate representation of reality.
現実を正確に表してはいないだろう
Our current theories about the Universe, namely general relativity,
現在の宇宙に関する理論
「一般相対性理論」では
are just not able to describe or explain them.
これらを説明できないのだ
The curvature of space becomes infinite, density becomes infinite,
空間の曲率は無限大となり
密度は無限大となり
and our rules just don't make sense.
我々の理論の枠組みを越えている
The singularity has no surface or size,
特異点は表面も大きさもなく
something like a divide-by-zero error in the universe.
宇宙を0で割るとエラーになるようなものだ
So singularities might not even exist or be completely different things.
つまり特異点は存在しないか
全く別のものかもしれない
But this is all we know right now, from the best prediction we have,
これらが現在知っていることの全てであり
from our best current theory of spacetime.
現状最高の理論から導かれたものだ
Also, basically everything you've ever heard about black holes, even in this video,
また、この動画を含め
ブラックホールの話は数学上の都合で
is about theoretical black holes that aren't spinning, because their math is so much easier.
回転していない理論上の存在として
語られていることに留意しよう
But since black holes were born from dying stars that were spinning extremely quickly in their last moments, as far as we know,
ブラックホールは死にかけの星が
超高速回転しながら生まれたものなので
all black holes in the universe should be spinning right now.
全てのブラックホールは回転しているはずだ
At incredible speeds too, up to 90 % the speed of light.
それも光速の90%という驚異的な速さで
This means in reality, black holes are even more screwed up than they usually get credit for.
つまり現実のブラックホールは
理論上よりもさらにめちゃくちゃなのだ
The singularities of rotating black holes are even wilder.
回転しているブラックホールの
特異点はよりワイルドだ
The rotation causes them to swell outwards into a sort of ringularity.
回転により膨らんだ点は
リング状特異点と呼ぶべきものとなり
This rotation is so powerful, that space itself is dragged along.
空間そのものを引きずるほどの
驚異的回転力をみせる
This creates another region around spinning black holes, called the Ergosphere
回転するブラックホールは
どれだけ頑張っても静止できない
where it's impossible to stay still, no matter how hard you try.
エルゴ球という空間を周囲につくりだす
Like a rushing whirlpool of spacetime, the tide is irresistible
時空の渦が押し寄せ
その潮流は逆らえず
and black hole makes you orbit it whether you want to or not.
望もうと望むまいと
ぐるぐる回しにされる
Ok. So what will happen with black holes as the universe ages and dies around them?
なるほど、では宇宙の終わりには
ブラックホールはどうなるのだろう
Again, we don't know but have some ideas based on our current understanding of physics:
これもまたよくわからないが
現状の理論から言えることもある
Hawking radiation.
ホーキング放射だ
In quantum field theory the vacuum of space is boiling with quantum fluctuations.
場の量子論によると真空の空間は
量子的な揺らぎによって沸騰している
These fluctuations are creating matter and antimatter pairs of particles from nothing
この揺らぎは何も無いところから
物質と反物質を生み出し
which only exist for a very short time before annihilating.
ほんの一瞬存在したあと
消滅すると考えられている
When this happens near the event horizon of a black hole,
ただ、事象の地平線のそばであれば
one of these particles can fall in, stopping them from annihilating.
片方の粒子は吸い込まれるため
他方は消滅を免れる
The escaping particle is Hawking radiation.
こうして逃げ出した粒子が
ホーキング放射だ
Ultimately, the mass of this particle must come from the black hole,
これら質量の元は
ブラックホールによるので
so over eons black holes will shrink and radiate away.
幾星霜を経れば
ブラックホールは放射により縮むだろう
Hawking radiation is not the stuff that fell into the black hole,
これらはブラックホールへの落下物ではなく
it's new stuff, stealing mass from it.
質量を奪う別物なのだ
As the black hole shrinks the Hawking radiation gets stronger, faster and faster,
ブラックホールが縮むにつれ
ホーキング放射は強力になり
until what's left eventually evaporates in a flash of high energy radiation like a nuclear bomb.
最終的には核爆発のような
高エネルギーを放射し蒸発する
And then, nothing.
あとには何も残らない
But that won't happen for a long long time.
しかしそれはずっと未来の話だ
A black hole with the mass of our sun has a lifetime of 10^67 years.
太陽と同じ質量のブラックホールの寿命は
10の67乗年だ
Which means that it would take 10,000 billion, billion, billion, billion,billion, billion years,
つまり、1万×10億×10億×10億×
10億×10億×10億年かけて
to lose 0.0000001% of its mass.
0.0000001%の質量しか失われない
But most black holes are way more massive than our sun.
ほとんどのブラックホールは
太陽より重く
The most massive supermassive black holes in the centers of galaxies
銀河の中心の
超大質量ブラックホールなら
have lifetimes of 10^100 years.
その寿命は10の100乗年におよぶ
How long is that?
どれだけ長いことだろう
Imagine an hourglass, filled with one grain of sand for every single particle in the universe.
ある砂時計を想像しよう
中は宇宙の粒子1つにつき砂粒1つが入っている
Every ten billion years one single grain of sand falls to the bottom.
100億年に1度砂粒が
1つ落ちてくる
If we waited for the entire sand to fall down,
砂が全部落ちるのを見ていても
not even a percent of the lifetimes of these black holes would have passed.
ブラックホールの寿命は
1%も減っていないことになる
There is no good concept for our brains to grasp these time scales.
これほどのスケールの時間を理解するのに
我々の脳は役に立たない
Will we ever truly understand black holes?
ブラックホールを
真に理解でき
Really know what's going on inside them?
中の様子がわかる日は来るのか
No one knows.
誰にもわからない
We can only see their outsides, and the theories we have probably get their insides wrong.
我々はまだ外側を見ることしかできず
内側の理解は間違っているだろう
But it's okay to not know everything.
だが、それでいい
It just means there is still work to be done.
それはまだ、やるべきことがあって
It means there are still mysteries to solve and big ideas to think about,
解決すべき謎や
考えるべきアイディアが残っているということ
which is why humans do science.
だから人は科学をするのだ
In the end we at least can be sure that we still have plenty of time left to think about them
少なくとも、最後のブラックホールが消え去る前に
before the last one melts away.
それらを考える時間が
あることはわかっているのだから
If you want to continue thinking about black holes,
ブラックホールに思いを馳せるなら
you can do so by getting one of the many black hole related things the Kurzgesagt team made with love.
チームが愛情を込めて作った
ブラックホール関連グッズをお求めいただけます
Like our Black Hole Infographic Poster that teaches you all the Black Hole basics.
ブラックホールの全てを教えてくれる
インフォグラフィックのポスターや
Or our Choose Your Own Black Hole Adventure Poster
あなたを壮大な旅に連れて行く
that takes you on a spectacular ride and might leave you in need of a cuddle.
アドベンチャーのポスターなどです
In which case we made a Black Hole & White Hole Plushie.
ブラック＆ホワイトホールの
ぬいぐるみも
And if that's still not enough we also just released super comfy Space Socks,
ほかにも超しっくりくる
宇宙靴下や
very shiny Space Pins, a new Tote Bag & Pouch Set
キラッキラの宇宙ピンズ
バッグやポーチなど
and have many other great space related products that are all designed with love and care by us here at kurzgesagt.
宇宙に関する商品を
豊富に取り揃えています
Getting something from our shop is the best way to support kurzgesagt while getting something beautiful in return.
これらの購入は素敵なお返しをうけながら
チームをサポートする最良の方法です
Because of you we can keep making elaborate videos like the one you just watched,
皆様のおかげでこのような
凝った動画を作り続け
and release them for everyone.
無料で公開できるのです
Thank you so much for your support!
本当にありがとうございます